<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="noproj" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Removes camera distortions in a raw level 1 cube creating an ideal version of the cube.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    <i>Noproj</i> reprojects a <def link="level1">level1</def>
    <def link="Cube">cube</def> to correct for camera distortion.   
    The result is a level1 cube of the undistorted image in "Ideal" camera space.
    </p>
    
    <p>     
    Both cubes (FROM and MATCH) must see the same target. 
    Each requires <def link="SPICE">SPICE</def> data and should be processed with
    <a href="../spiceinit/spiceinit.html" target="_blank">spiceinit</a> prior
    to running <i>noproj</i>.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The Ideal camera geometry is derived from the MATCH	cube. 
    If the coordinate (lat/long) at each pixel in the MATCH cube maps to a lat/long 
    coordinate in the FROM cube, then the pixel value at the mapped coordinate in 
    the FROM cube is projected into the TO cube, with some interpolation due to 
    the distortion correction. 
    The default behavior is that any offbody pixels in the MATCH and the FROM cube
    are set to null in the TO cube. 
    See OFFBODY and OFFBODYTRIM for alternative options
    for mapping offbody data.
    Also see <a href="../cam2cam/cam2cam.html" target="_blank">cam2cam</a> as 
    <i>noproj</i> parameters are passed to <i>cam2cam</i>.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    This program will modify the cube labels for the Ideal camera.
    The original Instrument group is renamed OriginalInstrument and a new
    instrument group is created for the Ideal Camera.  The cube data
    is modified when this program runs <i>cam2cam</i>, creating the <i>noproj</i>'ed
    output cube with camera distortions removed.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Note that <i>noproj</i> will not propagate AlphaCube groups from the MATCH cube into 
    the TO cube since <i>noproj</i> is resampling the image.
    </p>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2006-11-14">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-02-13">
      Corrected for case where original instrument has negative affine coefficients
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-04-24">
      Added INTERP option, fixed SPECS parameter to allow user to override the default and enter a file, and updated the documentation
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-05-21">
      Changed category to Cameras
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-06-12">
      Corrected order of SetInputCube calls to set the MATCH cube first if is entered so that the labels on the cube to match are propagated from it and not the from cube
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-08-31">
      Turned off propagation of the polygon blobs because the file name contains "/" from
      the serial number and unix does not allow "/".  Also added a remove of the match file
      OriginalInstrument group written by cam2cam before writing the input OriginalInstrument.
      hijitreg reads the input CcdId from this group.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13"> 
      Removed references to CubeInfo
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2009-01-26">
      Completed applying summing mode to ideal camera by applying it to the sample/line translations.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2009-03-25">
      Fixed setting of et to correspond to first line of parent (Alpha cube)
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-07-06">
      Updated Spice members to be more compliant with Isis coding standards. References #972.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-09-10">
      This program will now modify the NaifKeywords object, if it exists, instead of the instrument
      group with the following keywords: TransX (becomes IDEAL_TRANSX),
      TransY (becomes IDEAL_TRANSY), TransS0 (becomes IDEAL_TRANSS), TransL0 (becomes IDEAL_TRANSL),
      PixelPitch (becomes IDEAL_PIXEL_PITCH), and FocalLength (becomes IDEAL_FOCAL_LENGTH).
      Fixes #1094.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2017-08-19">
      No longer propagates AlphaCube group to output cube. Fixes #4907.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2019-01-28">
      Add OFFBODY option to also project off-body pixels. Added the 
      OFFBODYTRIM option to not propagate target intersections in 
      the FROM image into the projection when they don't intersect
      into the MATCH view. Added use of unique temporary name 
      creation for the match file template to avoid file name
      collisions (e.g., when run in parallel in same directory)
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2021-03-31">
      Refactored app to be callable and converted its tests to GTests.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2021-05-06">
      Added checks for ray tracing options in UofA OSIRIS-REx ISIS code base.
      The keywords needed for Bullet to operate properly are RayTraceEngine,
      BulletParts, and Tolerance. These parameters must be included in the
      output label in order for cam2cam to run and subsequent use is consistent.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2021-09-22">
      Rework how temporary external files are identified in UofA OSIRIS-REx
      ISIS code base after use by cam2cam and ensure they are all deleted. Fixes
      #4813.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2023-12-14">
      Incorporated Kris Becker's 2021-05-06 bug fix above into USGS code base.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2024-01-09">
      Incorporated Kris Becker's 2021-09-22 bug fix above into USGS code base.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2024-08-07">
      Additional bug fix to address persistent temporary lbl file after
      running noproj. Fixes #5577.
    </change>
    <change name="Sarah Sutton" date="2025-04-30">
	    Incorporated Kris Becker's keyword additions OFFBODY and OFFBODYTRIM
	    of 1/16/2019 and 1/28/2019 from UofA codebase to Astrogeology.	
	    Added examples and updated documentation. Addresses #3602.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>cam2cam</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <oldName>
    <item>noproj</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This cube will have the camera distortions removed based on the correction for the MATCH file and output to the TO file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATCH">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <internalDefault>
             Match cube
         </internalDefault>
         <brief>
           Instrument cube to match
         </brief>
         <description>
           This is the level 1 cube whose labels will be converted to the Ideal instrument and used as the cube to match.  It must have only one band so use the input attributes to select the band to match.  For example,
           themis.cub+5
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SPECS">
         <type>filename</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Ideal camera specifications file
         </brief>
         <internalDefault>
             SystemDefault
         </internalDefault>
          <description>
           This file contains the specifications for the "ideal" camera based on the original instrument.   
           If no value is entered, the default specs file will be read from 
           "$ISISROOT/appdata/templates/noproj/noprojInstruments.pvl"
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.pvl
         </filter>
         <defaultPath>
             $ISISROOT/appdata/templates/noproj/
         </defaultPath>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will be a copy of the input cube with the labels modified for the Ideal Camera
          cubes.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Summing Mode">
        <parameter name="SOURCE">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>Defines how the summing mode in the output noproj'd file is obtained </brief>
            <default><item>FROMMATCH</item></default>
            <description>
                This parameter is used to specify how the summing mode is obtained for the output
                noproj'd cube.  The pixel pitch of the output file will be set to the summing mode times the pixel
                pitch of the input file.  The output pixel pitch is written to the labels of the noproj'd cube.
                Note::  The user can override the default using the USER parameter.
            </description>
            <helpers>
                <helper name="H1">
                    <function>LoadMatchSummingMode</function>
                    <brief>Load Output Summing Mode from Match file</brief>
                    <description>This helper button will load the default summing mode from the match camera </description>
		    <icon>$ISISROOT/appdata/images/icons/exec.png</icon>
                </helper>
                <helper name="H2">
                    <function>LoadInputSummingMode</function>
                    <brief>Load Output Summing Mode From Input file</brief>
                    <description>This helper button will load the output summing mode  from the input (FROM) camera </description> 
                </helper>
            </helpers>
            <list>
                <option value="FROMMATCH">
                    <brief>Get from input MATCH cube</brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will automatically determine the output summing mode from the cube to match specified using
                        the MATCH parameter
                    </description>
                    <exclusions>
                         <item>SUMMINGMODE</item>
                     </exclusions>
                </option>

                <option value="FROMINPUT">
                    <brief>Get from input FROM cube </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will automatically determine the output summing mode from the cube to match specified using
                        the FROM parameter
                    </description>
                    <exclusions>
                        <item>SUMMINGMODE</item>
                    </exclusions>
                </option>

                <option value="FROMUSER">
                    <brief> Get summing mode from user  </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option allows the user to specify the summing mode to be applied to the input file pixel pitch (mm/pix)
                        to determine the output pixel pitch.
                    </description>
                </option>
            </list>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="SUMMINGMODE">
            <type>double</type>
            <brief>Summing Mode</brief>
            <description>
                Specifies the summing mode to multiply times  the input file (FROM) camera pixel pitch (mm/pix) to determine the
                output noproj'd file pixel pitch (pixel size in mm).  This value is written to the output file labels
            </description>
            <minimum inclusive="yes">1.0</minimum>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
        <parameter name="INTERP">
            <type>string</type>
            <default>
                <item>CUBICCONVOLUTION</item>
            </default>
            <brief>Type of interpolation</brief>
            <description>
                This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input in cam2cam.
            </description>
            <list>
                <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
                    <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
                    <description>
                        Each output pixel will be set to the pixel nearest the calculated input pixel.
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="BILINEAR">
                    <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
                    <description>
                        Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
                    <brief>Cubic Convolution interpolation</brief>
                    <description>
                        Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
                    </description>
                </option>
             </list>
        </parameter>

       <parameter name="SAMPEXP">
           <type>double</type>
           <default>
               <item> 0.0 </item>
           </default>
           <brief> Sample expansion percentage </brief>
           <description>
               This parameter expands the size of the output file in samples beyond the default size to prevent cropping of the 
               undistorted image.  The undistorted image may be larger than the raw distorted image.
           </description>
       </parameter>

       <parameter name="LINEEXP">
            <type>double</type>
            <default>
                <item> 0.0 </item>
            </default>
            <brief> Line expansion percentage </brief>
            <description>
                This parameter expands the size of the output file in lines beyond the default size to prevent cropping of the 
                undistorted image.  The undistorted image may be larger than the raw distorted image.
            </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OFFBODY">
          <type>boolean</type>
          <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
          <brief>
               Preserve offbody data
          </brief>
          <description>
               This parameter is provided to allow the user to selectively keep data
               in the FROM image that is off the target body. 
               When OFFBODY is FALSE (the default), pixels off the target body 
               in the FROM cube will be NULL in the resulting TO cube.
               When OFFBODY is TRUE, for pixels that are off the target body, 
               the RA/DEC coordinates in MATCH are mapped to 
               FROM. If the RA/DEC is within the FROM cube, the output pixel DN value
               is interpolated from the FROM cube to the TO cube. See also OFFBODYTRIM.
          </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OFFBODYTRIM">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
              Set select pixels in OFFBODY mode to NULL
        </brief>
        <description>
              When using OFFBODY mode, there are situations where the coordinates in
              the MATCH do not intersect the target body (i.e., the pixel does not have
              a latitude and longitude).
              In that case, the MATCH RA/DEC coordinate is mapped into the FROM 
              image field of view. 
              If the RA/DEC maps to a FROM sample/line and OFFBODYTRIM=TRUE, 
              the sample/line is checked for intersection with the target body. 
              Pixels that intersect the body will result in a NULL output pixel value.
              Otherwise, the FROM pixel value is interpolated and propagated
              to the output pixel.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  
   <examples>
     <example>
      <brief> Demonstrate the effects of the OFFBODY and OFFBODYTRIM parameters </brief>
      
      <description>
        In this example, <i>noproj</i> is used to remove camera distortions from two images acquired
        by the OSIRIS-REx NavCam during a particle ejection event at Bennu 
        (<a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aay3544"
            target="_blank">Lauretta et al., 2019</a>).
        Example images are 20190106T205618S792_ncm_L0 (long exposure) and
        20190106T205611S433_ncm_L0 (short exposure). The images are imported from FITS files and
        converted to ISIS cubes with <a href="../tagcams2isis/tagcams2isis.html" target="_blank">tagcams2isis</a>.
        Both cubes are initialized with <a href="../spiceinit/spiceinit.html" target="_blank">spiceinit</a>
        using the bennu_g_00880mm_alt_obj_0000n00000_v020.bds global shapemodel found in the 
        <a href="https://arcnav.psi.edu/urn:nasa:pds:orex.spice" target="_blank">OSIRIS-REX SPICE KERNEL bundle</a>.    

        <h3>Input images</h3> 

        <img src='assets/images/example1/noproj_example1_inputImages.png' width="2600"/>

        <h3>Command Line for running <i>noproj</i> on long exposure image</h3>

        <img src='assets/images/example1/noproj_example1_cmdLine1.png' width="2600"/>

        <p>
          Here, OFFBODY=TRUE and OFFBODYTRIM=FALSE to preserve the pixels in the space around Bennu,
          including the ejected particles. Note that the same cube is used for both FROM and MATCH
          parameters. 
        </p>

        <h3>Command Line for running <i>noproj</i> on short exposure image</h3>

        <img src='assets/images/example1/noproj_example1_cmdLine2.png' width="2600"/>

        <p>
          Here, OFFBODY and OFFBODYTRIM are FALSE. OFFBODY is set to FALSE to set all pixels off the
          target body to null. The <i>noproj</i>'ed long exposure output is used as the MATCH cube. 
          The specifications file (specs.pvl) is required because the MATCH cube has been
          run through <i>noproj</i> and is now identified as an "Ideal" camera in the label.
          The specifications file contains the undistorted (Ideal camera) detector dimensions. 
          In this case:

          <pre>
            Object = IdealInstrumentsSpecifications
  
              Group = "IdealSpacecraft/IdealCamera"
                DetectorSamples = 3050
                DetectorLines = 2404
              End_Group
  
            End_Object
            End
          </pre>  
        </p>

        <h3>Output images</h3> 

        <img src='assets/images/example1/noproj_example1_outputImages.png' width="2600"/>
        
        <p>      
          Null pixels are shown in yellow to illustrate the undistorted image outline.
        </p>

        <h3>Mosaic the <i>noproj</i>'ed long and short exposures</h3> 
        
        <p>
          To see the ejected particles <em>and</em> the surface of Bennu in the same scene,
          we mosaicked the short exposure cube on top of the long exposure cube using 
          <a href="../handmos/handmos.html" target="_blank">handmos</a>. 
          In the image shown, both <i>noproj</i>'ed cubes have been contrast-stretched, 
          but only at a rudimentary level. This example does not
          reproduce the full processing required to generate the figure in the article
          referenced above, but it does illustrate a case where it is necessary to 
          preserve off-body pixels.
        </p>
          
        <h3>Particle ejection observations mosaic</h3> 

        <img src='assets/images/example1/particle_mosaic.jpeg' width="600"/>

        <p>
          OSIRIS-REx NavCam image 20190106T205611S433_ncm_L0 combined with 20190106T205618S792_ncm_L0.
        </p>

     <h3>To Reproduce This Example</h3>        
        <p>
        Download the <a href="assets/files/process_navcam_particle_images.sh" target="_blank">shell script</a>, 
        the <a href="assets/files/BulletEngineSelect.pref" target="_blank">ray tracer</a> 
        preference file, and the Ideal camera 
        <a href="assets/files/specs.pvl" target="_blank">specifications</a>  
        file linked here. 
        The ray trace preference file sets the ray trace library to 
        <b>Bullet</b> rather than <b>NAIF DSK</b> (default for shape models with a ".bds" 
        file extension) as Bullet will detect occlusions. 
        The specifications file defines the size of the distortion-corrected NavCam image,
        which after running <i>noproj</i> is identified as the "Ideal" camera model.
        Before running the script, place the preference and specification files 
        in $ISISROOT. 
        The script will download and move the OSIRIS-REx DSK (shapemodel) kernel into $ISISDATA. 
        See the
        <a href="https://github.com/DOI-USGS/ISIS3/blob/dev/README.md#Mission-Specific-Data-Downloads" target="_blank">ISIS documentation</a>
        for instructions on downloading $ISISDATA for a specific mission.
        </p>
      </description>
      </example>          
   </examples>
</application>
